Guide to the Carl Van Vechten Letters to Saul Mauriber
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Carl Van Vechten Letters to Saul Mauriber
1943-1965
YCAL MSS 1144
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.9
(17 boxes)
The Carl Van Vechten Letters to Saul Mauriber date from April 1943 to December 1965, and include typed and manuscript notes, letters, greeting cards, postcards, and telegrams documenting their relationship over twenty years.
Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Boxes 16-17: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Carl Van Vechten (1880-1964)
Carl Van Vechten was a writer, photographer, collector, and patron of the arts. Born in Cedar Rapids, Iowa, on June 17, 1880, Van Vechten developed an early interest in literature and the fine and performing arts. He attended the University of Chicago, and wrote for several Chicago newspapers before moving to New York City in 1906. Over the next five decades he established himself as a journalist, critic, novelist, photographer, and cultural icon. He wrote music, dance, and theater reviews in New York and Paris for The New York Times and The New York Press, and for magazines and journals including Trend, Vanity Fair, Crisis, New Republic, and Esquire. He authored numerous books including, Music After the Great War (1915), The Tiger in the House (1920), Peter Whiffle: His Life and Works (1922), The Blind-Bow Boy (1923), The Tattooed Countess (1924), Firecrackers (1925), Nigger Heaven (1926), Spider Boy (1928), Parties (1930), and Sacred and Profane Memories (1932), most of which were published by Alfred A. Knopf.
His 1907 marriage to Ann Snyder, a friend since his youth in Cedar Rapids, ended in divorce in 1912. On October 21, 1914 he married Fania Marinoff, an actress who had immigrated to the United States as a child from Russia. They were married for fifty years. A family inheritance received in 1927 provided Van Vechten with the means to support himself and Fania, and freed him to pursue his interests without financial constraints. During the 1920s, Van Vechten was introduced to members of the artistic and cultural movement that would become known as the Harlem Renaissance. He enjoyed frequenting the clubs, restaurants, and salons of Harlem, and he began to develop friendships among members of the Black community. His 1926 novel, Nigger Heaven, was inspired by his visits to Harlem and its residents.
Beginning in the early 1930s Van Vechten devoted much of his time to photography. In his home studio he produced hundreds of photographic portraits of his friends and acquaintances, as well as other world figures whom he photographed by invitation and by recommendations from mutual friends. He and Fania developed a large multicultural network of friends and acquaintances in New York, throughout the United States, and abroad. The Van Vechten apartment became a meeting place for established and developing writers, visual and performing artists, publishers, educators, social activists, and others. Throughout his life Van Vechten developed close friendships with women as well as intimate relationships with men.
As a collector, Van Vechten acquired important collections of books and manuscripts, particularly those relating to African-American arts and literature. In 1941, he established the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts and Letters at Yale University, in honor of the writer and close friend who had died in 1938. In 1947, Van Vechten established the Anna Marble-Pollock Collection of Books about Cats at Yale. He also gave to Yale additional individual books and manuscripts, as well as a large group of his personal papers. He established and/or donated material to collections at other institutions including Fisk University, Howard University, the University of New Mexico, and the New York Public Library (including personal papers dating from 1833 to 1965). Carl Van Vechten died in New York City on December 22, 1964.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Beverly Hill on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2018.
Scope and Contents
The Carl Van Vechten Letters to Saul Mauriber date from April 1943 to December 1965, and include typed and manuscript notes, letters, greeting cards, postcards, and telegrams documenting their relationship over twenty years. Mauriber lived in Brooklyn with his mother, Sadie Mauriber, and as he had no telephone for many years, he and Van Vechten communicated by mail on a frequent basis. In his letters Van Vechten noted appointments with sitters for photographic portraits with which Mauriber was to assist; described his social activities and news of mutual friends; and commented on Mauriber's work, travel, and family issues. Van Vechten expressed his love for Mauriber often, and his messages included plans to meet him alone or to attend dinners or performances with Van Vechten's wife, Fania Marinoff, and friends. Enclosures include third-party letters from mutual friends and others; newspaper clippings regarding the arts, celebrities, fashion and other subjects; advertisements for performances and exhibitions; ticket stubs (which Mauriber collected); performance programs; postcards (many of which were photographic postcards by Van Vechten); and miscellaneous objects. The collection also includes postcards, greeting cards, and letters from Marinoff to Mauriber (in which she described her travels, thanked him for a gift, or sent birthday or holiday greetings), and greeting cards from the Van Vechten's to Saul's mother.
Saul Mauriber (1915-2003)
Saul Mauriber was born in New York City, and lived most of his life in Brooklyn. He worked as a clerk in retail establishments including Bergdorf Goodman department store. Mauriber also studied fashion, and for a time designed and made clothing for friends and acquaintances. Later in life he was a real estate investor. He met Carl Van Vechten in November of 1942, when both were volunteers at the American Theatre Wing's Stage Door Canteen for servicemen during World War II. At a gathering and photo session of Canteen volunteers at Van Vechten's home, Mauriber demonstrated an interest and ability in assisting Van Vechten with the photography. Shortly thereafter, he became Van Vechten's photographic assistant in his home studio, setting up lighting equipment and assisting with the printing and organizing of photographs. Their friendship grew into an intimate relationship which continued for twenty years. After Van Vechten's death Mauriber assisted with the organization of Van Vechten's photographs and the donation of them to various cultural and educational institutions.
Mauriber, Saul
- Letters, 1943-1965, undated; 6.3; (15 boxes)
  - 1943 April 23-1945 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
  - 1946 January 23-1947 December 28 (Box 2, Folder 10-21)
  - 1948 January 5-1949 July 31 (Box 3, Folder 22-30)
  - 1949 August 1-1950 February 28 (Box 4, Folder 31-37)
  - 1950 March 2-September 30 (Box 5, Folder 38-46)
  - 1950 October 1-December 31 (Box 6, Folder 47-52)
  - 1951 January 2-1951 June 4 (Box 7, Folder 53-60)
  - 1951 June 9-December 23 (Box 8, Folder 61-66)
  - 1952 January 6-July 9 (Box 9, Folder 67-76)
  - 1952 July 10-December 28 (Box 10, Folder 77-87)
  - 1953 January 3-1954 January 9 (Box 11, Folder 88-97)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes children's book, Heads Bodies & Legs by Denis Wirth-Miller and Richard Chopping (London: Penguin, 1951) in envelope postmarked December 16, 1952; third-party letter from "Dot," likely Dorothy Mauriber, Saul's sister-in-law (1953 December 29)
  - 1954 January 11-1955 December 18 (Box 12, Folder 98-107)
    Includes third-party letters to CVV from George Kennedy, Christopher Isherwood, Bruce Kellner, Dick Wardell, Edward Donahoe, and Walter Burr Van Vechten enclosed with letters from CVV to Mauriber
  - 1956 January 8-1958 December 18 (Box 13, Folder 108-116)
  - 1959 January 9-1961 December 28 (Box 14, Folder 117-126)
  - 1962 September 22-1965 December, undated (Box 15, Folder 127-135)
    Includes Christmas card containing a manuscript note from CVV to Mauriber dated "Christmas 1965"; and a folder of undated photographic postcards of CVV, Mauriber and others by CVV, some of which have manuscript notes from CVV on the versos
- Restricted Fragile Material, 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 6 (Box 16, Folder 136)
  - Box 1, folder 9 (Box 16, Folder 137)
  - Box 2, folder 10 (Box 16, Folder 138)
  - Box 2, folder 12 (Box 16, Folder 139)
  - Box 2, folder 15 (Box 16, Folder 140)
  - Box 2, folder 17 (Box 16, Folder 141)
  - Box 2, folder 18 (Box 16, Folder 142)
  - Box 2, folder 19 (Box 16, Folder 143)
  - Box 2, folder 20 (Box 16, Folder 144)
  - Box 2, folder 21 (Box 16, Folder 145)
  - Box 3, folder 22 (Box 16, Folder 146)
  - Box 3, folder 24 (Box 16, Folder 147)
  - Box 3, folder 26 (Box 16, Folder 148)
  - Box 3, folder 27 (Box 16, Folder 149)
  - Box 3, folder 28 (Box 16, Folder 150)
  - Box 3, folder 29 (Box 16, Folder 151)
  - Box 3, folder 30 (Box 16, Folder 152)
  - Box 4, folder 31 (Box 16, Folder 153)
  - Box 4, folder 32 (Box 16, Folder 154)
  - Box 4, folder 33 (Box 16, Folder 155)
  - Box 4, folder 34 (Box 16, Folder 156)
  - Box 4, folder 35 (Box 16, Folder 157)
  - Box 4, folder 37 (Box 16, Folder 158)
  - Box 5, folder 38 (Box 16, Folder 159)
  - Box 5, folder 39 (Box 16, Folder 160)
  - Box 5, folder 41 (Box 16, Folder 161)
  - Box 5, folder 42 (Box 16, Folder 162)
  - Box 5, folder 43 (Box 16, Folder 163)
  - Box 5, folder 46 (Box 16, Folder 164)
  - Box 6, folder 47 (Box 16, Folder 165)
  - Box 6, folder 48 (Box 16, Folder 166)
  - Box 6, folder 49 (Box 16, Folder 167)
  - Box 6, folder 51 (Box 16, Folder 168)
  - Box 6, folder 52 (Box 16, Folder 169)
  - Box 7, folder 54 (Box 16, Folder 170)
  - Box 7, folder 55 (Box 16, Folder 171)
  - Box 7, folder 56 (Box 16, Folder 172)
  - Box 7, folder 57 (Box 16, Folder 173)
  - Box 7, folder 59 (Box 16, Folder 174)
  - Box 7, folder 60 (Box 16, Folder 175)
  - Box 8, folder 61 (Box 16, Folder 176)
  - Box 8, folder 63 (Box 16, Folder 177)
  - Box 8, folder 64 (Box 16, Folder 178)
  - Box 8, folder 65 (Box 16, Folder 179)
  - Box 9, folder 67 (Box 16, Folder 180)
  - Box 9, folder 68 (Box 16, Folder 181)
  - Box 9, folder 69 (Box 16, Folder 182)
  - Box 9, folder 70 (Box 16, Folder 183)
  - Box 9, folder 71 (Box 16, Folder 184)
  - Box 9, folder 72 (Box 16, Folder 185)
  - Box 9, folder 73 (Box 16, Folder 186)
  - Box 9, folder 74 (Box 16, Folder 187)
  - Box 9, folder 75 (Box 16, Folder 188)
  - Box 9, folder 76 (Box 16, Folder 189)
  - Box 9, folder 77 (Box 16, Folder 190)
  - Box 10, folder 78 (Box 16, Folder 191)
  - Box 10, folder 79 (Box 16, Folder 192)
  - Box 10, folder 80 (Box 16, Folder 193)
  - Box 10, folder 81 (Box 16, Folder 194)
  - Box 10, folder 82 (Box 16, Folder 195)
  - Box 10, folder 83 (Box 16, Folder 196)
  - Box 11, folder 89 (Box 16, Folder 197)
  - Box 11, folder 90 (Box 16, Folder 198)
  - Box 11, folder 91 (Box 16, Folder 199)
  - Box 11, folder 92 (Box 16, Folder 200)
  - Box 11, folder 93 (Box 16, Folder 201)
  - Box 11, folder 94 (Box 16, Folder 202)
  - Box 11, folder 95 (Box 16, Folder 203)
  - Box 11, folder 96 (Box 16, Folder 204)
  - Box 11, folder 97 (Box 16, Folder 205)
  - Box 12, folder 98 (Box 16, Folder 206)
  - Box 12, folder 99 (Box 16, Folder 207)
  - Box 12, folder 100 (Box 16, Folder 208)
  - Box 12, folder 101 (Box 16, Folder 209)
  - Box 12, folder 102 (Box 16, Folder 210)
  - Box 12, folder 104 (Box 16, Folder 211)
  - Box 12, folder 105 (Box 16, Folder 212)
  - Box 12, folder 106 (Box 16, Folder 213)
  - Box 13, folder 108 (Box 17, Folder 214)
  - Box 13, folder 109 (Box 17, Folder 215)
  - Box 13, folder 110 (Box 17, Folder 216)
  - Box 13, folder 111 (Box 17, Folder 217)
  - Box 13, folder 112 (Box 17, Folder 218)
  - Box 13, folder 113 (Box 17, Folder 219)
  - Box 13, folder 116 (Box 17, Folder 220)
  - Box 14, folder 117 (Box 17, Folder 221)
  - Box 14, folder 118 (Box 17, Folder 222)
  - Box 14, folder 119 (Box 17, Folder 223)
  - Box 14, folder 120 (Box 17, Folder 224)
  - Box 14, folder 121 (Box 17, Folder 225)
  - Box 14, folder 122 (Box 17, Folder 226)
  - Box 14, folder 124 (Box 17, Folder 227)
  - Box 14, folder 125 (Box 17, Folder 228)
  - Box 14, folder 126 (Box 17, Folder 229)
  - Box 15, folder 127 (Box 17, Folder 230)
  - Box 15, folder 129 (Box 17, Folder 231)